hi welcome back to lumram i'm sorry we
took a long break
we were just having fun at dime mountain
and again
you know it looks kind of possible that
we could
have our next retreat in october right
the october
retreat there it looks like a good
chance it could be
we could do some things here at thai
mountain if the virus
and the vaccinations are cooperating yay
so we're going to do a meditation
together
and this is called a nyam chi saying
yamchi
and this is a different way
a traditional different way of teaching
the alarm room
and that's where you try to elicit
a any motion okay so then it
we did the we etched the
silicon okay we scratched your brain we
tried to
put some uh what do you call it
some tracks in your brain with all the
pictures
we finished with the pictures okay and
that's a necessary
beginning to meditation you got to get
content
before you can get feeling so now
you know let's say we've etched we've
scratched the pictures into your brain
right so it's now it's time to bubba
it's time to have an experience of those
pictures okay and we're gonna try that
we're gonna try that in a meditation
that takes more time and it takes more
silence
okay so i'm not gonna talk much i'm
gonna take you to a certain
track that we already scratched in your
brain
and then you're gonna and i'm gonna feel
it
okay we're trying to feel what we
tracked
okay and that's called empty so that's a
progression in the alarm room
traditional progression
you go from idea to feeling
okay all right all right here we go
so please sit up straight
i just like to put a small smile on my
face and
for me uh that's almost
the main preliminary to a meditation is
to
feel relaxed and
feel hopeful okay put a small smile on
your face
that will loosen up your forehead
hopefully and then it'll be easier to
meditate
make sure your hands are comfortable you
know after 50 years
of trying to meditate
i realized what you want to do with your
hands is get them out of the way
you can so however you want to hold your
hands
hold them in a way that
you don't notice what they're doing okay
get them out of the way pull in your
lower
abdomen very very helpful for meditation
which strengthens your back
and we're going to accomplish that
tightening of your lower abdomen by
taking t 10 deep exhales so
you're on your own 10 deep
exhales keep exhaling past your normal
limit
to where your abdomen tights up and
that's that's going to be good for your
posture okay here we go
now we're going to go to that first
picture
it was a young person
who had just been accepted on a sports
team
and we know the picture
and we know what it means it means
uh if you if we work hard
then one day during our prayers during
our meditations
we will have this awesome experience
that we are actually
in a few minutes traveling
from planet to planet and by the way
planets it's not like they're all lined
up
waiting for you to jump from one to the
other
i mean a planet
with people on it it's extremely rare
you might have to travel
many light years many millions of miles
to jump to the next planet so imagine
planets millions of miles apart
covered with living things
remember we're not just talking about
people
all kinds of living creatures birds
things that crawl in holes under the
ground
whales fish
bacteria okay
imagine a whole planet teeming with
life millions of miles to the next one
and you are sitting at home
on your meditation cushion and finally
after years of hard work with lamrim
and other practices
it all pays off and suddenly
you have this experience that in a few
minutes
in less than half an hour
you are leaping from one planet to
another
each jump is a million miles millions of
miles
when you arrive on a planet
you are sitting down
with each separate living creature
individually one by one each ant
each bird each human
you are taking the time
right if someone takes time
to be with us we feel good if someone
takes 15 minutes or half an hour
to give us their full attention to some
question we have a problem we have
we feel so lucky right but imagine
that you are able to give your time
and your full attention to
a hundred billion
different people in a
in less than a minute okay imagine try
to imagine that
okay and imagine what it feels to be
a person who has had that experience
okay so this first meditation
we're gonna it's called in the diamond
way
using the result as the cause
we're gonna pretend we're having that
experience
and that will burn a pathway into our
mind
that later we will have the experience
so try
to imagine approaching a world
teeming with life covered with different
kinds of living beings
and imagine that you
give full attention and time
to each one of a hundred billion
beings one by one within a minute or
something
just try to feel it
and and imagine yourself doing it that's
all
it's gonna be unnatural it's gonna be
a stretch but if you imagine it
it will help it happen later okay here
we go
we'll spend about five minutes here
now imagine you've come back to this
world
finish that journey sitting on your
meditation cushion
finish the class classes for today
and then you just started to do all the
things you have to do today
but imagine the glow around you
imagine the
the holiness around you
that you just
comforted a hundred billion
living beings
one by one with full attention
and imagine there's a very
beautiful glow
around you
a very tangible
holiness or power around you
because even in your imagination
you just imagined
connecting with 100 billion
needy beings
individually this morning
then imagine what it's going to be like
the rest of today you are walking around
for the rest of the day a person
who just took care of a hundred billion
people when we visit someone in the
elderly home right we feel
or we go to the prison and we teach
prisoners i i always feel special
for a few hours after that but imagine
this morning you
confident 100 billion people
and then imagine
the effect you're going to have
on people you meet today okay they will
meet you
they'll say hey there's michael there's
alex
there's ellie but
subconsciously people always know
who's loving them or who's feeling
intense love subconsciously
people will sense that you
went to a 100 billion
prisons this morning or
or care facilities this morning and
your presence in the world
for the rest of today will bless this
world
okay so imagine that imagine you are
a bodhisattva
and your presence in the world for the
rest of the day
will bless this world this will be a
better world
because you are doing your normal day
today okay
let's spend a few minutes there imagine
the things you have to do
the things you have planned for the rest
of today
and imagine the unspoken
effect you will have on the people
around you
the rest of today not because you really
touched 100 billion people but because
you
imagined it which already
gives you a special glow okay here we go
imagine going through the rest of the
day
as a person who just took care
of a hundred billion people this morning
okay imagine what it feels like the rest
of the day
imagine some of the things you're
supposed to do today
here we go
then we'll take three deep exhales and
imagine golden light
coming from your breath touching
people throughout this world and
blessing them
then we'll take a stretch
so we had 10 pictures right we went to
two of them i think and uh
you can try that for a few days okay
all right then any questions about that
meditation
in the room here no okay we get to go in
no questions good okay
there's a few uh
you know when you have a big war and you
have a big battle and then uh the
battle's over
and people go around and
take stuff from the dead bodies and
stuff it's kind of mop-up operation
there's some mop-up operation in this uh
um section from tonkapa jetson kappa
so i'm not going to spend too much time
on it
but somebody tries to argue
well if it takes those self-made buddhas
another lifetime to get to their nirvana
can you really say it was a result
of the teaching that god on the wheel of
life
and so god was like don't bother me with
dumb questions all right
i mean basically he's he's like of
course
it took a lifetime but it's okay it took
another lifetime
but it's okay you can still say it was a
reaction to the teaching they got okay
that's not a big problem all right uh
yeah it's not that it has to happen in
this in half hour later
okay
and and so kappa says you know don't try
to
minimize the role
of the person who taught them dependence
origination they are still their father
and mother
they still gave birth to them as
in a spiritual sense okay even though it
was a delayed birth what do you call
that
past term like 10 months
pregnancy it's still a pregnancy come on
all right okay um
then somebody says does it have to be
dependent origination
and uh jensen copper says
you know not you could say they are
children of the teaching
and you'd still be okay all right so
don't don't get hung up on the subject
all right it was the teaching
that gave birth to the
to the self-made buddhists okay we have
a picture pow of
a lady under a tree
okay he says
when you think of how buddhas give birth
to their students who reach spiritual
goals
you don't really have to get hung up on
the subject matter
the teaching gave birth the teaching
gave them birth okay
all right now we reached
another big subject in tonkapa
and that's okay
you covered the first half
chandra kirti's words of praise
right at the beginning of the book you
covered the first half that was how
listeners and self-made buddhists
come out of buddha but can you tell us
where
the buddhas themselves came from okay
the moms
the moms gave birth to twins
listeners and self-made buddhists but
where'd the mom come from okay that's
the second half of this whole
exercise right
which is why pabong karimpichi mentioned
this text
in the long run because he's gonna say
you need bodhichitta
you need bodhisattvas you need crescent
moons in the world
to become
full moons okay and you should honor
crescent moons beyond full moons
and maybe the full moons should drive
around the crescent moons in the back of
the station wagon we were telling a
story about
the buddhists who drive around there's a
story in scripture
that bodhisattvas are so important to
the process even though they are not
buddhists yet
they are so important in the process
that the buddhas
will will carry their chariots
if there's no horses around the
buddhists will drag the chariots
while the police officers are goofing
off in the turret
because their police officers are so
vital to the process
okay and we had an example and we don't
need to talk about it
all right
now somebody says okay
if the self-made buddhists and the
listeners
take their holy birth from the buddhists
well where the buddhists come from who
gives birth to the buddhists
okay and uh then tsongkhapa quotes
china kirti directly and says
they're totally enlightened buddhas
right we have to now we have to add
those
adjectives right adverb adjective
totally enlightened buddhist
the full buddhists take their birth from
the body's office
okay that's where they come from did
somebody
ask a question okay here it is
uh how can you say
that buddha's come from bodhisattvas
if the nickname for a bodhisattva is
guilty
child of the buddhist if the nickname
for
bodhisattva is child of the buddhists
how can you say buddha's come from
bodhisattvas
what you have a kid and then the kid has
you
it doesn't make sense got it you know
the guy's like
what are you talking about you have a
kid and then the kid has you
it doesn't make sense you know either
the bodhisattvas are the children of the
buddhas gelse or
or the buddhists come from the buddhist
office and the buddhists are the
children of the body surface but you
can't have it both ways
on campus it's weird okay
so someone has this problem and we have
a picture of a father
you know who's the child in the picture
yeah did the guy with the beard come
from the girl with the smile
or did the girlfriend with a smile come
from the guy with a beard
or did they come from each other which
is what you seem to be seeing chanda
kirti
if you say buddhists come from
bodhisattvas
okay all right got it it's weird
who's the parent in this picture
okay all right good chang said
look i agree gil say
i agree gil say i agree the bodhisattvas
have to come from buddhist i agree and
can't get any
but still we can say bodhisattvas are
the cause for buddhists
from two points of view he says okay got
it
yeah i admit that uh
bodhisattvas are produced by one or more
buddhists
individual individual bodhisattvas are
produced normally
by one or more buddhas okay any
bodhisattva in this planet
has been produced by shakyamuni buddha
directly or indirectly okay but
from two points of views from two points
of view
all buddhas are also products of
bodhisattvas
okay anybody want to take a shot
[Music]
in what sense she said to be a buddha
you have to be caused by a bodhisattva
but in what how pro by what present
because the process of becoming a buddha
you first have to become good yeah so i
would call it i like to call it the
evolution theory
to turn into a buddha you got to start
by being a bodhisattva
only bodhisattvas can turn into
buddhists okay
with regard to a single person's
spiritual evolution they always go
through the stage of bodhisattva
before they hit the stage of buddha you
got the first one
you got the easy one okay in that sense
bodhisattvas always give birth to
buddhas
so in a sense buddhas are the kelsey
and bodhisattvas are the are the mom
okay but there's a second
sense in which bodhisattvas cause
buddhist
that's more difficult i think it has
something to do with
in order so you can't become apparent
oh dang that's too deep that's a third
one
yeah they arise neutrally yeah yeah
that's called duckbigue to call someone
a
a parent the kid has to come out first
yeah
that's true you guys are giving a very
negative answer
but there's an easier one
let's go through it okay it'll be sexy
you'll like it you'll like it i i really
enjoy
tom cropper's explanation which is here
we go
here's the first one the one that you
said okay uh
spiritual evolution demands that we go
through the stage of being a bodhisattva
before we reach buddhahood
in that sense in that first sense
bodhisattvas have borne buddhas
right so here we go
if we talk about period of
time in a process if we talk about
a period of time in a longer process
okay
then in that sense changs and namsange
nanki
bodhisattvas are the cause of the
buddhas right so they
beget the buddhas they give birth to the
buddha
they should shape and negotiate
the stage of buddhahood is a
spiritual result of the stage of being a
bodhisattva
in that sense bodhisattvas give birth to
buddhists okay
the kid in the picture gave birth to her
father
okay all right
and then he's quoting a scripture that
says of oh
all buddhas come are preceded by a
period as a buddhist
okay that's he quotes who does he quote
i don't remember i think it's chandi
kyoti's uh auto commentary
kia pena nikki that's a nearly kiku
what's a nearly kiku
material cost in the in the growth of a
tree it's the
seed good two kinds of causes tim for a
hundred dollars
material cost you don't even need the
tibetan i just need the english
there's the seed that turns into the
tree but what's the second thing that
makes the tree grow
what the biochar
the fertilizer the water the sunlight
okay those are called
ken right uh tun ken
uh contributing factor okay there's
contributing factors
biochar rain sunlight
the effort of the farmer and then
there's the
material cause which is the seed which
material cost is kind of defined as
the thing that turns into the tree the
farmer doesn't turn into the tree
the sunlight doesn't turn into the tree
the seed turns into the tree
but the rest of it helps make it happen
right
okay cool so in a
material cost sense bodhisattvas
turn into buddhists bloody suffers are
like the tree seed
and then buddhas come out of that scene
right the tree
but is there a way to now here's the big
question
sexy question is there a way that a
bodhisattva
acts as a contributing cause for a
buddha
and he says here's some copper's answer
uh and this is a beautiful story and
it's a nice place to end today
okay uh historically
if you go back to a time
of which even buddhism has no
[Music]
good records okay in the history
in the life history of this buddha on
this planet
there was a time before
recorded buddhism like forget
everything we know before that okay
go back billions of lifetimes
okay there was a guy named manjushri
okay and at that point
zillions of lifetimes ago he was not a
buddha
he was just a really cool bodhisattva
and he met a guy who was destined to
become called
shakyamuni
okay got it a bodhisattva named
manjushri
met a normal dude named
who's gonna be called shakyamuni
and he taught him the dharma
okay a normal bodhisattva
who wasn't a buddha yet by any scripture
according to any scripture okay
tantra says manjushri is already a
buddha
you know sutra says he's just a
bodhisattva
but forget that back in the days when he
really was just a bodhisattva according
to everybody
okay he wasn't a buddha yet he taught a
dude
who was gonna become shaky mooney and
shakimuni got there first
okay got it this guy named manjushri
taught a guy who's going to become
shakyamuni
who wasn't the bodhisattva the
bodhisattva taught the guy who wasn't a
bodhisattva
but the second guy worked harder and he
passed the bodhisattva he became
bodhisattva
and then he became a buddha now
manjushri becomes the contributing cause
for
this buddha got it cool
so in that sense this buddha was born
from
a bodhisattva less than a buddha
a full buddha was born from someone who
is less than a buddha
as a contributing cause meaning sunlight
what was the sunlight he taught him he
taught him the dharma
my jews we taught our buddha the dharma
when our buddha was just a plain schmuck
got it that isn't that a beautiful
example so that's the second sense
in which a bodhisattva can
give birth to a buddha that's a second
sense what was the first sentence
everybody goes through bodhisattva hood
before they get the buddhahood that's
like the seed for the tree but everybody
also who becomes a buddha ran
into bodhisattvas maybe even back when
they were helping
and and was influenced by them to become
who they are now
and in that second sense all buddhas are
also
children of bodhisattvas cool it's
so you can think this classic division
into material cost the stuff that turns
into the tree
and then the contributing causes the
fertilizer the sunlight which are the
other body softens hanging around the
universe okay got it
all right let's see here uh
[Music]
then the guy comes back he says i still
don't like it that
the same kid can be the parent of their
parent it's still uncomfortable for me
okay it's still uncomfortable for me
that
the kid could be the parent of the
parent you know
and some kappa you know
he spends time saying you have to look
at it from two different points of view
that's all and as you guys said
the existence of a child defines someone
as a mother
so in that sense the mom has to wait on
the child
to be the mom and in that sense
the mom has been born from the town
okay always it's always like that
okay that's very nagarjuna
let me see you're going here i'm
thinking we can
we're gonna well we're gonna go on and
we don't have to stay with the tibetan
but uh we only have a zero minutes
uh and i'll leave you with something to
think about okay and i know it's
we aren't even supposed to be studying
this it's not part of the law room
we just decided it was a good place to
go because pabonko
rinpoche used this lines
in islam room to talk about
the importance of bodhichitta right it
creates buddhas
so
why okay a hundred dollar question
why did chandi kirti mention this topic
at the beginning of his book
yeah good he was bowing down to
yeah you're supposed to bow down to
somebody at the beginning of a book
and that's always a big decision for a
buddhist author to make
who am i gonna about which bow down will
be most relevant to my book that i want
to write
so he chooses someone to bow down to
and he bows down to the bodhisattvas
okay last question then we're done for
today okay
who else agrees that it's important to
bow down to body surface
who drove the station wagon
okay good yeah yeah okay
it's you got to get in this mood that
bodhisattvas are so
important that buddhists will shine
their shoes
okay bodhisattvas are so
important to the welfare of this
universe
that buddhas who already went beyond
that
will come back and do their laundry or
something
got it okay cool
so bodhichitta must be important if the
buddha will come back and do your
laundry
buddhing must be something cool okay
that's all
that's the whole retreat right we're
trying to advertise buddy today
okay all right okay we'll see you guys
tomorrow